Hello, and welcome to the Python Exchange. My name is Cameron Riddell, and I will serve
as your host this afternoon. Today, we are joined by a special guest, Rich Ianan, whom
you all may know through his various open source projects, Great Docs and Great Tables.
If there's a good chance that his project is great, then Rich has had a hand in making
it. But before I share more about our guests, let's first introduce our panelists who
will help us drive discussion. First up, today, we are joined by, as per usual, James Powell.
James, for anyone who has not yet had the opportunity to meet you, can you answer this
question for our audience? James, what is one of your favorite Python topics as of today?
Hi, everybody. As Cameron said, my name is James Powell. It's a pleasure to be here.
One of my topics that I've been thinking about a lot recently related to Python is, what
might come after Python? I know that might be a very controversial thing, but I've been
thinking a little bit of what the next language, the next hype, the next thing might be.
Fantastic. Well, James, I definitely want to hear your thoughts on that. However, we
have some other hosts who are happy and chomping at the bits to share their favorite Python
topics as well. Next up, let's hear from Tom Caswell. Tom, can you answer the same question
just so our audience can get to know you a little bit better? And that is, what is one
of your favorite Python topics as of today?
I think one of the things I'm most excited about is the new debugging, the new profiling,
the sampling profile that is coming in Python 3.15. That is a thing I'm looking forward
to being able to use for good.
That's the Tachyon profile, right?
Correct.
Oh, fantastic. I know Pablo spoke a little bit about that at PyCon US, and I missed the
talk, so now I have to go watch it. But excellent to have you here today with us, Tom.
Let's also hear from our host, Tani. Tani, same question to you. What is one of your
favorite Python topics as of today?
I think it's my background in AI and ML. I think it's definitely related to how can we
build Python-based pipelines that can receive the fast-paced advancements of AI and ML and
new things coming up. So how to make sure that we can do this transfer learning appropriately
across different projects.
That is fantastic. It sounds like a very complex topic of very complex interest, so I love
hearing that, Tani. Thanks so much for taking the time today to join us.
Last up for our host panelists, we are also joined today by Dan Allen. Dan, can you also
share with us what your current favorite Python topic is?
Sure. I'm excited to see how the free threading work forces me to rethink the assumptions
that have been true about Python for as long as I've been doing it. I guess that pairs
well with the sampling profile that's going to check my intuition.
The alternate version of that, Dan, is all the bugs that will be found due to the security.
We're just waiting for the re-implementation of the GIL then and Python 3.16 so we can
have it back.
They need to strip out the JIT work first.
Yeah. Excellence. Well, these are our host panelists who, as I mentioned, are going to
help us drive some discussion. And what will we be discussing? Well, we are going to be
discussing a topic that our guest today, Rich Iannan, is very passionate about.
But before Rich shares about that, I want you to all get to know Rich just a little
bit better.
Rich is a software engineer who spent a long time thinking about how we actually present
information in documentation, especially when it comes to tables, summaries, and making
complex things easier to scan and understand.
He's worked across the open source ecosystem for years, starting primarily in R and recently
contributing heavily in Python as well.
In fact, there's a good chance that you have heard of or even use some of the tools that
he's worked on.
Today, Rich will be sharing with us about GreatDocs.
But instead of hearing about GreatDocs from me anymore, Rich, I would love you to fill
in our audience with all of the details.
So Rich, take it away.
I will do that.
And what I got is actually a bunch of slides and some browser tabs because I figured it's
good to show GreatDocs.
Otherwise, it just becomes a theoretical thing.
But also, it's kind of funny because I also wanted to just, like, entirely show GreatDocs
and not have any slides.
But I thought that was too weird.
So we're going to have a mix of both.
So I'm going to share my screen.
All right.
Here we are.
Let's get this going.
Excellent.
Oh, you have to do it twice.
It's just a weird thing.
Okay.
Sweet.
So GreatDocs.
It's a documentation framework in Python for Python packages.
And we're going to begin with some background.
Challenges with Python package documentation.
Here's one.
It's often the first thing people look at before they commit to actually using the software.
So it might be a deciding factor as to whether they use your software.
Okay.
So documentation, it has to be good to keep existing users engaged.
Otherwise, people may turn to alternatives with better docs.
More lately, an agent might read the docs first.
So we probably should keep in mind that, you know, a doc site might be better suited for
agents.
So I got some responses for people that do docs.
Three cheese points.
One is, like, design for a good initial impression.
Organization, presence of reference and guides should be there.
And then to keep the users engaged, we need good authoring tools and use those good authoring
tools for the reference and guides.
And finally, we need things suited for agents, like pages and markdown form, lms.txt, and
maybe even documenting skills and having skills available.
Okay.
So many tools, I'm talking about tools that make documentation for you or help you make
documentation.
They get you to a pretty decent look and feel, and then they may not go beyond.
So let's take a look at a few docs pages.
These are not all Python related.
I just kind of surveyed, you know, some of the internet and looked for some examples
of docs.
And here's one.
It's actually a package I work on.
And these docs were made by me.
They were made by Cran.
And we can learn a lot just by looking at what not to do with docs.
If you look on the left-hand side, the contents list is not arranged in any sensible manner.
It's alphabetical order, which is good if you know the name of the thing, but otherwise
kind of bad.
The logo is missing, if you look in the top left.
That's not a great good initial impression.
The topography is not that great.
And the tables, they're hardly recognizable tables.
They're not styled.
There's no lines.
But there are indeed tables in this.
Okay.
That's some problems.
This is from a Python package.
And you may not need me to say it, but if you look from the left side, a lot of those
objects are encroaching on the main content area, which is obviously not good.
And also the code examples are oddly indented, almost centered.
And it's got this problem of many, many methods on a single long page.
And maybe that's the fault of the documentation generator.
It doesn't give you the option to split those out in some sort of gripped manner.
But that's where we are with this.
Here's another one.
It's actually for a LaTeX package called long table.
And it's a PDF.
So you don't really get the benefits of documentation on web pages.
You can't get there with a Google search, typically.
The command reference, there actually is one on some page, is pretty terse.
And it's all stuffed into a summary table.
And because this is essentially a guide, there's no expectation of conventional sections.
There's a command reference, because the person just deigned to create one.
Here's another one for a project called juice.
And I was confused about this one, because I looked for a doc site.
But essentially the docs are on the readme, the GitHub readme.
So that's a problem.
There's no generated API reference.
So the issue there is that this could drift from the actual code.
It's basically handwritten.
And it only ever reflects main.
So anyone on an older version can't read docs for that version.
So that's what we have here.
So I showed a few egregious examples of maybe not-so-great documentation.
But I want to say, a lot of the documentation now is really, really good.
Look to the right.
FastAPI, Polars, FastMTP.
These are great.
Like Seaborn, these are fantastic.
Authoring features that they use to support teaching.
There's a lot of polish there.
But still, there's still challenges that remain.
Like building docs for AI agent consumption.
There's a little bit there.
You can sort of see that in FastMTP.
But it's kind of like only the beginnings of that.
So a while back, when I was doing this survey,
I thought, maybe there's an opportunity here to do something.
So enter great docs.
I figured I would throw my hat in the ring
with a new Python documentation library.
So some of the design goals I had early on
is that with it, you can create a beautiful, complete site
with almost no configuration.
Like, getting close, but you need a little bit.
But, you know, we try to gloss over that a bit.
It'll have depth features and control when you need that stuff.
So we have a lot of features.
You don't need it right away, but you might use that later.
And a big thing was, it's got to be ready for human readers.
Like, be really, really nice if you're just reading it.
And also be useful for AI agents.
Because a lot of times, they're just thrown onto some docs.
And, you know, it's up to them to make sense of it.
Okay.
So when I was looking at stuff,
I looked for inspiration everywhere.
I looked at things like Packagedown, MATLAB.
A lot of good ideas, like, wherever you look.
So I'll show you what I liked from each of these.
Packagedown, that's an R thing.
MATLAB, that's just the MATLAB docs.
Hexdocs, that's for Elixir.
And I think Erlang as well.
And Vue.js, which is its own thing.
Okay.
So Packagedown is kind of where it started for me.
It made good docs to default for R.
And I did a lot of R stuff.
So basically, I use this a lot.
A really cool idea that they had a long, long time ago
was this right sidebar.
And it just made a lot of sense to me.
It just has metadata for the package.
It has the authors, some useful pages like the guides,
the contributing guide, citation, license.
You know, good stuff.
So I basically, I stole that.
It's in GreatDocs now.
That's like a little screenshot of GreatDocs.
I grabbed that.
Okay.
But, you know, Packagedown.
Like I said, it's my home turf.
I built tons of R packages like these ones here.
And they all have a Packagedown site.
And I'm pretty familiar with it.
So a little bit biased, you might say.
What else did I steal?
Well, the homepage sidebar, like I showed you.
The idea of a zero-config build.
Almost zero-config.
Conventional reconfiguration.
Like if you have certain files in certain spots,
the framework will just, like, look for them
and then use that in making the docs and the build.
Beautiful publishable defaults.
And Packagedown's site looks wonderful
the instant you make it.
And this wonderful package API index page,
which is kind of cool.
It kind of gently puts you into, like,
the reference section.
It gives you an index and some descriptions.
And lo and behold, that's in GreatDocs now.
Sort of like a comparison of the two things.
Okay. MATLAB.
I gotta admit, I don't really like MATLAB.
I used it before in the past.
Not really a big user.
But I love their docs because they really go so deep
in their docs.
It's all, like, super accentuated at the top.
They tend to overexplain,
which I think is kind of a good thing.
Like, see, for every sort of, like, overload
or use of, like, read table,
they have a separate description.
So it's like, well, they just went the extra mile there.
They have tons of examples.
Like, this page is really, really long.
Like, they have so much in there.
And I kind of appreciate that.
And the parameters.
Nobody really documents them
like MATLAB does.
They actually, like,
if you look here, they give a name, of course,
to each argument, which is wild
to me, and pretty useful as well.
They give lots of room
for examples. They have them in disclosures
so you can just fold them up because there's so many of them.
And, yeah,
again, I love the idea of a short description for each parameter.
Okay. And Elixir.
They have, like, this
very consistent set of documentation
pages.
And it just looks good
because of the structure, I think.
So especially the sidebar.
I mean, what I took from this
is, like, you know, navigation is very, very
important. Like, if we can just simplify
it and make it, you know, like, really, really
good, I think that's, like, one big
sort of, like, piece of
documentation that's solved.
And they also,
like many other frameworks,
they put narrative guides
as, like, you know, top level with, like, you know,
a reference section. So it's, like, super front and center.
It's, like, right there on the left.
And it's, like, there, the minute you land on this page.
Okay. Another one is the Vue.js
docs. They're so
easy to navigate, and they're really
great at teaching new users especially.
They also get
navigation right, which is really nice.
I like the fact that their
sidebar is, like, very flat
and easily scannable.
They have good use of space. They don't make it too complex.
There's no nesting.
The header itself is not clickable. It's basically just,
like, a group, essentially.
The CTAs they put
at the end of different sections, they're wonderful.
They're basically, like, paths, like, learning paths
you can take, and they do that quite a bit.
And they have these in-page callouts
that are used for tips that
you can divert
yourself to, like, a different learning path.
Like, this one here, like, watch
interactive video.
I think that's great.
I looked at all these tools. I was really
inspired, and some big
concepts I used were, like, package downs,
ease of use, MATLAB's insane
depth,
Elixir's structure, and Vue.js' clarity.
Great docs. We tried to incorporate
all these things along with some well-considered defaults,
and what I think
we do a bit differently with this project
is beautiful out of the box,
tries to look good on mobile as it does
on desktop widths, and
document as many things as possible,
especially for LLMs.
Like, the API for, of course,
CLI, if you have it, MCP
servers, and also
document agent skills, if you got those as well.
Okay, so I'm going to take you out of these
slides, like I said I would,
and show you the great docs site.
Okay, first I'll just show you, like, the landing page,
like, essentially the GitHub repo.
It's basically here, under
great docs, and there you can find
a link to the actual great docs
site. Of course, you can search for it,
and you'll get there. I'll just show you in this tab.
This is, like, the great docs site.
I just want to show you they can have light mode or dark mode.
Kind of cool. And here, again,
is the right sidebar with different links
to go to different places,
like you can view the package on PyPI,
you have links inside GitHub to, like,
report a bug.
Cool things, like here, which is essentially
the developers, we have, like, links
you can send me an email if you want.
Kind of nice that it's all here,
and we have things like, of course,
like affiliations,
and also, like, the company as well,
showing us, you know, like, who's involved
in this whole enterprise.
Another cool thing is, if you have certain
files, like, kicking around,
great docs will look for that
in the directory, or other little places
that these files may be. For instance,
right here, contributing guide, it looks for
contributing.md, it basically publishes
it in a separate page. Code of conduct,
project roadmap, if you got it,
roadmap.md, security.md,
your license as well.
I just want to show you one of these. I'll show you license. It's kind of cool.
It'll take you to this page
right here. We've got this little thing here,
and it'll actually tell you little details about licensing
things for, you know, because it knows
about the MIT license, and, of course,
you know, it'll just tell you a little bit more
about it.
In case you're not, you know, you come up against, like,
a license you don't really know,
can you use it or not, you know, it basically
dispels some uncertainty there.
So,
really cool.
I also want to show you, like, the user guide
right here on this. You can go to
this page in the top-level nav,
and you get sent to the user guide, and
it has a sidebar right here
which floats, and you can go
to any of these pages, and
we have user guide stuff there.
And the cool thing is we have things like page tags
right here, and lots of
authoring tools for things like,
you know, bits of, like, code.
It could be any type of code. You can specify
that. This entire site uses
Cordo. It basically builds on top of Cordo,
so we get lots of Cordo affordances
and authoring tools, and we basically
build on top of that and enhance a few things
as well.
So, let me show you a few more things on this
site. Another thing is
the function, like, basically the reference section,
and here we have
a reference
item table preview inside of
great docs, but you can actually go up here.
When you start on this page, you start with the
index, and you can dig deeper,
and you can specify
how to organize your left sidebar
with different groupings. You can specify,
of course, the different methods
inside one page, or you can
split them out to different pages like this.
And the cool thing about this is it gives
your readers
a lay of the land on this index page.
You can have rich descriptions.
You have these short summaries for individual
methods or classes or what have you.
It's kind of like a good sort of easing
in instead of just, like, being hit with
the very first thing.
One more thing I want to
show you is that we document all sorts of stuff.
We document, of course, a Python API.
You have
that available if you offer one.
We will document that as well,
and it's pretty good. We basically
have a reader and writer for that, which is
not that bad. And more
lately, we've been doing MCP as well.
If you have an MCP server in this
project, in any project,
we will look at that and write those
API pages out.
One more thing I want to show you
is the changelog. I find this
pretty important.
It keeps users up to date. Essentially, what we do here
is we look at your releases
on GitHub and essentially
create a page, and every time
you fire off a build, it just looks, again, for
any updates to changes, like
releases.
Okay, and I'm going to go back to my slides.
Great.
I'm thinking, just
because of the age we're in, we now have to think
a little bit more about documentation
for the AI era
because now your documentation is going to
be read by agents, whether
you like it or not.
What we need to have
are skills that
agents can discover and load.
We don't have to have that, but what we do is we offer
a basic skill.
If you want it, you can opt out of it.
It's essentially just a
very basic skill that we can write
essentially just as a guide
to your project.
But if you
have custom author skills, like you've
made the skills yourself, GreatDocs will
find that and actually publish
that, and it's quite nice. If you have multiple
things, you'll see there's actually some
information here, and it'll show you all the
components of each skill.
Okay, and I touched upon
MCP reference. If you do
have that, like an MCP server,
it'll actually just go ahead, unless
you opt out, and make it MCP
reference pages for you.
And this is a thing
that you can also opt out of, but it's nice to have.
Essentially, it is LLM's text and
LLM's full doc text
full API. You don't have to
write this yourself. GreatDocs will just do this.
LLM's doc text, if you don't know it,
is not a very big file. It's essentially
like a sitemap. It's just like a very simple
text file that agents sometimes look
for. And LLM's
full is essentially
the whole API inline,
and it's quite a bit
bigger, obviously, depending on the size of the
package, but LLM's
do sometimes look for that as well.
Okay.
So, I mentioned, I touched upon
agents as the first readers.
They're increasingly reading your docs before any
human does, which
changes a lot. If an agent can't parse
it, your users will feel it in some small
way, maybe a big way.
There'll be more turns, longer
conversations, maybe
some bad decisions.
So, in a
small way, maybe in a big way, docs are
sort of like an API service now,
because decisions are made on
your docs sometimes.
And you're
writing for humans and machines alike
in this scenario.
So, I came across
this really interesting site,
this project, whatdoagency.runtype.app.
It's a tool for
getting an agent or
simulating LLM
looking at a site. You just pop
in a URL, and I did so here
with a Great Talks page.
And it shows you whether
it can find the things that
would help an agent. So, it's really
small here, but I zoomed in here.
So, it does find LLM's text, it does find
LLM's foldout text, and it finds
markdown pages, essentially
a version of the page which is not .html
but .md, so a markdown version
of the page, which is useful.
So, we can see
from this that, yeah,
we can also test
different agents and see the same results.
So, it's being used, and
this sort of
in a way validates that.
Okay,
moving aside from AI and agents,
I have to confess I love features,
and I stuffed a lot of them into Great Talks
and tried to make each one good
and useful and something that I would use.
So, one of them
I'm going to show you is
I'll show a few of these live,
and I'll just show you a few of these in slides.
But a big one is Term Show,
and I made that because I was really
frustrated with showing or demonstrating
CLIs. The tools that
were available were kind of good,
but it has major shortcomings, I thought.
So, I built a thing
which I'll show you in more detail
to help teach users your CLI
or your TUI application.
Another
big thing was Lightbox,
a full-screen Lightbox with zoom and gallery.
Sometimes you have images,
it could be diagrams, what have you,
and you just want to show things and
make it labeled and such.
So, I built a thing for that.
Another big thing was Table Preview and
Table Explorer, which I'll get into.
Essentially showing tables. It occurs
to me that sometimes we have lots of data
either in our package
or you transform some data and you want to show
the results. That's where this comes in useful.
So, I'm going to show you
right now,
just give you an inkling of what Term Show is.
So, usually, like I said,
CLI and TUI demos
usually mean a GIF or a video.
They can be huge, sometimes blurry
because the text is not really well recorded
or you're recording at a low bitrate.
You often can't
select the text and you often
can't even pause the playback.
So, you want to rewind
a bit, but you have to wait
until the next go around if it's a GIF.
Very frustrating.
So, I built a thing where
you just record your terminal activity,
you get a file, and then
there's also a paired YAML file.
This is for a configuration and presentation,
essentially, like the way you want to show it.
And, as you imagine,
it can get pretty crazy editing
YAML file to make it just right.
So, what I did was also I created
an editor for this. It's a
browser-based editor,
and it allows you...
It's almost like a little final cut for terminal
presentations, and I'll show you that in the
demo pretty soon.
Okay.
This is great, but what
users, like viewers, see
is sharp
SVG animation playback. It's got
its own full-featured player.
It's a lot like a video player.
And chapters, annotations,
you can have those in there, and you can
teach with that. You have all the tools
to demonstrate what your
CLI does and show
workflows.
So, I'm going to show that to you right now.
Okay.
So, I've got a tab open right here called Term Show
Editor, and here's a video I made a while
back. And, essentially, you can scrub around
and see almost like the live
video of your recording.
And you can just add
chapter marks. I can just double-click here, add a
chapter mark, and I can label it
new chapter, for instance.
And
it's kind of cool. Now I can scrub around and see I'm in
new chapter up here.
Very nice. You can always just hit play
to play back, which is kind of nice. You sort of
see it live. This is like an emulation of the final
thing.
You can add things like cuts. Say you don't want
to see a bunch of the video, just double-click here,
change the width of this, and you
can cut out some of the
extra dead space if you want.
So, if I start playing back, it'll just jump over
that, which is cool,
because sometimes you just have a lot of, you just stutter
over certain things, and
your terminal,
your demonstration is a bit overlong.
You might just want to cut bits out.
We also have something called
snippets. What that does
is it shows you in the
top right corner,
right here, you can have a little button, and you
can have text that's copyable. Say, for
instance, the command. You can
just have users click that, and they can
grab that command and put it in their terminal
if they need it. And it's shown at the right
time and in the right place up here.
So, really cool. And there's
also other things I'm not going to show you, like highlights.
You can sort of annotate pieces of
the actual terminal
characters and such.
The boxes around things.
The thing I want to show you also is, this is nice, but
what if you wanted to
just see it, how it would look on a page?
There's a preview button here,
and what it does is it just goes back,
of course, and does a render.
And this is how it actually looks inside the player.
And this is actually good, because I get to show you the
player, which is kind of neat. You can pause it,
scrub around, go to the chapter
marker here, click here, and you see
new chapter I just made. And this is
essentially an unsaved state, so before you even
commit it to save, you can just look at it
right here and go to the end.
You can change the player speed in case you like to go
really fast.
But this is kind of nice. Before you even
commit to rendering it,
you can make sure it's just right.
So that, in a nutshell, is
Term Show and the Term Show Editor.
I'll go back to my slides.
All right.
Okay, so
it doesn't end there in terms of features.
There's lots of features.
A big one I wanted,
I'm really into tables.
I have this project called Great Tables,
so definitely tables is kind of
my bag. But I think it's
useful to have that in documentation sometimes,
without importing Great Tables
or some other table library.
So I did something called
Table Preview and Table Explorer. Two different
things, but they're kind of
cut from the same cloth.
Table Preview is kind of like a simple
static table. It gives
you a small preview of the data, usually
like
ten rows, or it could be the
first, fifth, five rows, and the last five
rows. And it shows you
things like column types,
and it's pretty smart about being
wide, but not too wide, in terms of column
width controls.
And the really good thing about it also is that
you can import from many different formats,
like we're talking about DataFrames,
CSV files, JSONL, Feather
files, Parquet.
It's really great in terms of importing.
Okay. If you need a table,
it's a bit more interactive, full-fledged.
Table Explorer might be what you need.
So in this case, you have something
that's JavaScript-enabled.
It has all the things you might expect, like sortable
columns. You can sort by multiple columns.
It has buttons for downloading
the filtered and sorted data,
and a means to copy as
CSV text. And the filtering interface,
I'll show you how it looks when you actually have
some filters in place. You just click
the Add Filter button, and it presents
to you a small interface, which
depending on the column type,
will present different options for filtering.
And then they just appear as these tokens
on the field right there, which you can
remove, or you can add
more. So it's really
quite nice.
The lightbox thing is
basically born from frustration
of showing a few images,
and I figure it's a nice thing to have
in documentation. You never know when you'll need it
until you need it.
So what
it does, basically, you click
on an image, it brings you in this view, and
it just makes it large, essentially.
And if you have a gallery, and
you can have a gallery, you can just use the arrow keys
to page through the gallery.
And you can have dark mode,
image swap, so you might have
for instance, images for light
and for dark mode, like a pair.
You can have before and after
comparisons, which basically presents to you
this slider.
And another cool thing, which I'm not really showing here, is annotations.
You can have certain regions of an image
annotated, having dots and
callouts.
It's really small on the top right, but this is
zoomed in on the controls.
And we offer things like, of course, zoom,
the ability to copy image.
You can download the image, and the really cool thing is
getting a link to the image. So basically the link
will just mean, if you provide that link to someone else
and they follow it, it'll bring that
person to exactly this lightbox
view.
Okay, wrapping up.
So I want to conclude with a few points.
Great docs. It tries to be nice by default,
but powerful when you want more.
I kind of believe there should be a tradeoff
between an easy setup and having
depth control. So
great docs has sort of been designed to give you both.
Just a thought, I think we should treat documentation
as a product, put a lot of weight
on it. It's really what
people and agents judge your
project on before they really commit to using it.
So it deserves some design
depth and care.
Okay, this is a bit of
a spicy statement, but I'm going to say it anyway.
So your documentation is now kind of like an API
for agents as much as people.
So when an agent is
sometimes their first reader,
often, you might say, things like
skills, mcp docs, lms.txt,
they're kind of like table stakes
now. They stop being extras and become
required, you might say.
Great docs, they
teach you. They don't just describe things.
So if you have things like runnable examples,
callouts, and guides, which are
top level with your reference,
you might even have
terminal
presentations, they're all there to
actually teach your users.
And being good on mobile,
it shouldn't be an afterthought. Docs should be
just as good on a phone as they are on a desktop
for human readers.
This is why things
like parameter tables, sometimes they're
put in tables and you get
a very long parameter on the left side
and description that wraps over multiple lines
on the right.
Probably shouldn't do that on mobile.
There's some thought there to make it
read better and have better
architecture
of the information
constrained with devices.
So I want to say thanks.
Check out Great Docs. It's
available in GitHub under
positivegreatdocs.
And if you do try it out, let me know how it goes. I'm really interested
in people that do try it out, and I
really want to help people if there's
issues at all.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, Rich, and thank you for the
tour of Great Docs.
Let's jump into our discussion.
I'd love to open things up to
our audience as well. So if you're in the audience
listening in, then please go ahead.
You can submit your questions in the Q&A
widget, and we'll have them read aloud
for Rich and our panel to discuss.
In the meantime, while those questions
are coming in, I'd also love to open
this up to our host panelists here.
So if you have any questions from which
Rich has shared, please go ahead.
And James, I see that you have your hand up, so if you want
to kick things off, go ahead.
Let me first
premise this with two pieces of, I think, context.
The first piece of context is
I have recently been teaching myself
the Zig programming language,
and their docs are basically the
worst you have ever seen. They're out
of date, they're all machine-generated, they're
impossible to read through,
yet I still keep using the language,
and the docs don't really slow me
down that much, and I just kind of get used to writing
code. The second piece of context is
one thing that has always impressed
me about the work of
two of our colleagues, Tom and Dan,
is that even for very new projects,
I was always impressed by the volume
of documentation that they would
be able to put out for things like Kaputo
version 0.1 that have docs.
My question is,
there's some space in between
this really good docs and
absolutely terrible docs, where the
project is actually successful.
How does one avoid
what appears to me
to be the vanity of writing
docs, that's something you do for yourself, you make them
look really beautiful, but avoid
actually getting users, developing features?
How do you find yourself
not falling into that trap?
June 2026, Great Docs, pkgdown
People talk about docs.
Usually what I see or disparaging posts like these
docs are just the worst, but occasionally you see
some like, you know, validation, especially if really
author, like, use Dr.
Craig was like, especially if you're the author, you feel
you feel good at, you know that's extra press per, you
know, like if it's hard enough to get traction, you know
in Python projects or any project.
So I'll take a win wherever they can get it.
Absolutely.
Now, Dan, I see you here, your hand up, but before we
get to you and your question, there's a question from
the audience and that is rich.
Is there a preferred or supported style for documentation
slash doc strings that works the best presumably with great docs?
Hmm.
Well, actually it supports three of them, like NumPy doc,
um, uh, Google doc, um, is that right?
Google form and, um, RST.
So you choose one actually during introspection, it actually
determines through a simple sort of a heuristic, what you're
actually using and it'll just like say it'll set that and then
otherwise it kind of gets into like a quirks mode where it
tries to like correct, uh, it does, it does a pretty good job.
Um, if you have mixed documentation styles.
So I say, just choose one that's good.
And, uh, another thing that great docs does if this is great
doc specific, obviously, uh, it'll actually run like examples.
Like if you use sort of like this quarter markdown, um, sort
of like notation, basic code fences and such, which is like
an extra thing on top.
I'm not sure how that reads without great docs in place is
if you're just reading doc stream by itself.
Uh, it's not worse than RST in terms of like just reading it.
Um, I would say choose any style that's comfortable with it.
I think the key thing, just write docs, like complete, uh, pick one
style and like just go to town on the docs, I would say, yeah.
Fantastic.
So it sounds like as long as you're using a common style, NumPy doc
and Google docs are pretty standard.
I think so.
Yeah.
Usually one, one, three.
Some sort of standard.
Yeah.
Perfect.
And then Dan, did you have a question on top of that?
Uh, you might be muted on zoom.
Sorry.
I thought I had that.
Um, I have a comment and a question.
I really like term show.
That's super interesting.
We've thanks.
Um, we do a lot of internal tutorials at NSLS two for staff, and we've
talked about generating videos out of those so people could revisit them.
But the problem with video content is it gets stale.
I like the idea of a terminal script that is version controlled.
So an API or best practice changes and I can just tweak it.
I've seen versions of this, I think called ASCII cinema or whatever.
And I really liked the full featuredness of term show.
It seems like it gets it to a level of like actual usefulness.
That's very cool.
Um, the, the two questions.
Did you think about synchronizing it with audio ever?
Yes, I did think about that.
So I left some space at the bottom of the term show editor for extra sort of like
timelines for new things.
Yeah.
Uh, audio definitely want the extra thing.
Basically it'll just be like a little snippets that you can like pull in and,
you know, arrange.
And of course, you know, it's huge, but I think it's important.
Uh, it's a, it's a teachable thing, um, to have audio besides like, just like,
you know, text call outs.
And I think it might even be in the roadmap, uh, which is, uh, you know,
sort of listed in the front page of great docs.
So yes, I have thought of it and I think it's a great idea.
And I think we, and I felt the same, um, I looked at the same sort of things
like, uh, it was VHS and ASCII cinema.
I've actually used VHS on a different site.
It's okay, but it takes longer than you expect.
It was just like little gifts or videos.
Um, cause actually it just runs your terminal with a script and then creates
the recording and it takes like a good long while.
Uh, but it's got the problem of like playback.
It's basically just like running these gifts, which are on repeat.
Yeah.
I know you've solved a lot of the things that made it like almost good.
I mean, I'm glad those other things exist, but like, I thought, Oh,
we're not quite there yet.
Maybe this I'll have a stab at it.
And yeah.
Okay.
So then second part of my question, uh, which is a bit blasphemous, suppose
that we're heavily bought into Sphinx or heavily bought into mist MD, but I
wanted to embed term show in one of those two sites.
Is that doable?
Not yet, but that's a plan as well.
Right now.
It's like a, it's only for great docs, which is a little unfortunate.
Right.
I don't know why I did that.
I maybe it's just like convenience and such.
Uh, but I'm, I'm thinking, um, I'm just going to have that be a separate thing
or, cause essentially it's, it almost kind of is right.
It just missing the exporting part essentially.
And like the embedding part.
Um, cause really you're just running great docs, um, my term show
and then like create essentially.
Yeah.
And then the other little tools there.
So the last missing pieces like is that, and yes, that'll be a thing pretty soon.
Cool.
That's my question.
Thanks.
Rich.
I had a question as I was looking through great docs.
Um, I have not yet used it to myself for a project.
We recently moved, uh, our open source project narwhals to use, uh,
Zensicle, um, but I did see that, uh, a little mention about, uh, the great
docs gauntlet, and I was wondering if you could tell us just a little bit more.
Yes.
Yeah.
So I take testing pretty seriously and, um, to like maniacal level.
So the gauntlet is essentially, um, a lot of small great docs sites.
Um, basically rendered, you know, sort of in serial and then like
creating their own page with a hub.
And, uh, I have a separate repo for that and it builds daily.
And, uh, it's a way of sort of like seeing what fails, you know,
catching regressions with all sorts of possibilities, cause it's really
hard to test like a large framework like this, um, really well, you know,
manually you have to something, you know, like basically like a test
harness or framework and that's basically what it is.
Yeah.
Um, and I try to see what kind of, I try to build lots of, you know, like.
Dimensions of coverage into that little tool.
So anybody can just see this.
I have now have a banner or like a little badge on the great docs, uh, repo
itself that'll take you there.
And, um, it's a great tool for other people to see, like, you know,
what can this thing do?
Is it, and also it's a good demonstration that this thing is, it's kind of tested.
Uh, and, um, uh, but I think, I think that the key thing is like getting
enough, like examples, uh, in there.
I think, I mean, there's a little bit over 300 now.
Um, that covers a lot, but every time there's new features, a few of
these have to be added, of course.
And, uh, I think it's really useful.
It's also a really quick way to sort of see that the new feature added, uh, in
a very sort of specific isolated build, uh, actually works like I can
quickly iterate on, on the thing.
Yeah.
So it's just testing.
That's very cool.
Thank you.
Uh, Isabella shared a link in the chat to it.
Oh, nice.
Nice.
Tanya, did you have a question as well?
Um, yeah, I think that, um, this one did go through slightly during the talk.
Um, but I was wondering, uh, if you could, um, elaborate a bit more about
kind of like having now the commentation moving towards not only being human
readable, but also machine readable.
Um, and you know, what are different strategies to evaluate both?
Um, especially I think something that we will be super interested in will be kind
of like that is skill generation feature.
Um, in like how agents can make use of it.
It's like, how can we evaluate how effective they are beyond them?
Maybe just being machine readable.
Yeah.
So the whole deal with skills being published there is kind of like, so like
if you have an agent look at the site, they can discover it on their own.
You may not even know that just there's a skill there or a set of skills.
And there's actually some, you know, it's version it's essentially it could be
versioned, um, but it might be just an extra thing that you have or your, your
library itself.
And, um, yeah, it's quite nice.
So you don't have to like, it's basically self-advertising.
It goes into a special directory or a hidden directory called, um, I think
well-known and then like skills.
And, uh, I've done some like basic evals of this and different agents do tend to
find it if you suggest to look for them.
Uh, sometimes you, you have to sort of lead it, but it's not quite, uh, great
for discovery yet, but I'm trying to be a little bit ahead of the curve in terms
of like, you know, having these out there.
It's also kind of, it's also, it's actually kind of useful to have as well.
Um, just to have transparency on what the package has.
So I'm, I'm of the mind, just publish everything on the doc site.
Uh, that's that could possibly be published and it's either going to be
useful for, for an agent or for somebody else or for yourself down the line.
Yeah.
Great.
Yeah, you're welcome.
Uh, piggybacking off of that, Rich, I was curious.
Um, I may, I may have missed this during your, your, uh, presentation earlier,
but is that done just by a serving both the markdown and HTML file just
separately, and then the AI will get pointed towards the markdown file.
Yeah.
Um, you're talking about just like the standard pages, right?
Having like a markdown version.
Yeah.
Essentially we have like a blue, like buttons there to switch to the mode, but
essentially each HTML page is paired with an empty page.
And so, um, an agent might look for an empty version of the page.
It's starting to become more common.
Uh, but if that's, if it doesn't do that, you can just point it towards it.
Yourself in terms of just going to that, you know, hitting the button where you
can copy the text and just fuse the agent.
So you have a few avenues to get like a, you know, a page, a page's
worth of content into an agent.
Um, so it might be self-discovery or it might just be like, you
know, a little bit of feeding.
Uh, but it's kind of like all there for all pages and you don't have to really
worry about, um, uh, it being there for, because it's automatically
there unless you opt out.
That's very nice.
Now I noticed, I also noticed that in your examples of good documentation, you
put, uh, Matplotlib's documentation.
We have Tom Castle from Matplotlib.
And so I was curious, um, what, what were some of those things that really make
that good documentation stand out that you were striving for to make
the defaults in great docs?
Yeah, I think a big thing, and this doesn't always get done is examples,
like rich examples with pros, you know, explain the example like before and
after, like a good setup for an example, like the, the code, the results, and
then some additional commentary on that.
I think that's like, uh, overlooked and has been for, for so long.
Uh, but it's really useful, really very useful, especially when it's as close
as possible to the thing and not just like a, you know, like a, like a
degraded version of that, that, that, that is valuable to me.
And not only that, like having a few examples, I, I tend to go a little
bit maximal on examples myself.
You don't have to, but, um, I think it makes, cause a user may just land on
that page, you know, like a API reference, API reference page, it shows
them the thing, but then it shows a lot of examples and you can get your
imagination going on what the thing that's above can actually do.
Um, so I think it's, it's kind of central.
And you can always stop reading, especially if the examples are at the
bottom, you're just like, okay, that's it.
That's enough.
So it's kind of like, you know, extras and more, I think more people have
found them useful than, than, you know, irritating.
So, and that's what I think is good in terms of, uh, good documentation.
If I can jump in playing devil's advocate bit, um, the problem we have in
Matplotlib is that we, we say our docs are both too big and too small and
that it does not cover everything, but what is there sufficiently large that
it's, it essentially becomes unapproachable.
So how do you go about organizing?
Right.
Well, just considering just math, like something with a scale of
methodology gallery, how would you organize that to make it actually
discoverable for a user that's not like getting lucky from a search engine?
I tell him that just the gallery itself, just the gallery, just gallery.
I think just sectioning is, you know, like essentially I know it can go and
it's huge and there's many topics, uh, but there has to be some sort of way
to section it such that there's some beginner level things and then you go a
bit deeper in the middle and you end off going, you know, with more use cases.
Type things.
Um, there's gotta be, I think there's gotta be some ordering and sectioning,
just make it palatable, those, those, those chunks, but sorry, uh, if you go
by complexity, you may find the user needs to go very deep in a very particular
functionality, but who's new to the library.
And so if you go by functionality, they may spend a long time wandering around
with a lot of examples they don't need.
Yeah.
I think really just to go like down, down a complexity in this way.
So how do you, how do you do recommendations on how to handle the
inherent, like cross tapness?
Yeah.
It's, it's tough with really big APIs and I've, I've, I've got the problem as well.
Uh, you can have some things like, um, what I found is, is good.
It's having lots of cross-linking, like essentially like interlinks
between different topics and have that be prominent, like, you know, if related.
Or you can have page tags as well, which I incorporate in great docs.
So basically you can go to like a separate page tags index.
And then so long as the page tags are sufficiently, you know, like, uh,
divided up and specific enough and has enough pages underneath them, you can
probably isolate the pages pretty well.
Uh, I think the thing of last resort might be search, uh, which is this keyword
search that you actually end up in a pretty good state there, but I think
tags like page tags might be, might be the way forward.
It's aside from interlinks and just good, good organization.
I think if you have all those things, um, even at very large APIs and possibilities
and how to use the API, um, you can get further, it's still gonna take more
searching, but that's just the nature of the beast, I think, when you
have very large, complex software.
Um, and James, I see you had a question, but, uh, before I give that to you,
James, Rich, can you explain what you mean by the difference between cross-linking
and page tags there?
Yeah.
Cross-linking would just be essentially interlinks, essentially like little
links embedded in the text, like the pros itself, uh, typically it's, it
might be in the middle of the page.
It might be close to like, you might have them standardized as like, you
know, see, you know, see more or, you know, like see also, uh, on page, or
you might have tags, which are typically the top of a page and they just like,
um, they're just like little things you can click and they take you to like,
an index with similar pages, essentially like a, like a sitemap or an index.
Um, and that might be good because you might want to go back and say like,
oh yeah, I want to see all the pages that have this tag, because this, this,
this is what I'm looking at right now.
So that's another useful way of organizing things.
Excellent.
Thanks.
Yeah.
And then James, you had a follow-up?
Yeah, I have a follow-up to Tom's question, because I know Tom, I have
joked with you more than once that I simply don't ever read documentation,
but that's not strictly true.
In fact, I end up reading an enormous amount of the units of documentation.
I never, unlike I suspect you and your colleagues sit down at the beach with a
manual or a man page in hand and read it linearly.
I consume these things in an extraordinarily nonlinear fashion, which
is why for me as a user, my entry point into the Matplotlib documentation is
either one, I'm going from Google or these days I'm asking LLM to find the
articles for me and then going through that.
From that perspective, the organization of things like the gallery is honestly
completely irrelevant to me because I'm never going to use that organization.
I'm going to reconstitute it myself.
What also gives me a little bit of a pause is when we're talking about the,
the, the LLM versus human use cases here, it seems that we're drawing a very
unimaginative contrast between two very strict modalities.
A human being is reading these documentation that a human being wrote
in the way that we assume that people read these, like printing it out and
reading it on the beach, or the LLM is doing it automatically.
And I wonder if there's not some middle ground by which the LLM can serve as an
automation tool to create a customized nonlinear pathway through the
documentation so that the organizational structure is no longer built into the
way in which the documentation has been written, but it's constructed by the LLM
as part of some kind of learning process.
Okay.
Can I respond or you go first?
I think one thing about the, that's a fair point about the, you know, search
engine or, or the robot to giving you links deep into the docs, but what you
lose there is the, um, I don't know how to do anything with the tools.
So that means you, you, it to first for search to have worked, which means you
typed words at a text prompt, you've actually described that plot with the
same words we use to describe that plot.
Whereas if you like go to our gallery and just like hit your scroll wheel and let
it run, you, you can very quickly see like, Oh, that's the one I want to go back to it.
And the, that serendipity of, I don't know, I don't, I know what I want, but I
don't know the name of it.
I don't know the words for it, but like, I know it when I see it is something that
I think is, is important not to lose, particularly for plotting, plotting tools.
Right.
I'm very, I'm very biased towards visual things here.
I never stumbled across something I didn't know even existed and then learn
something I didn't even know I wanted.
Right.
Um, and second for the, yeah, and I don't really have a comment on the second one
of using the robot to basically build you a custom documentation.
I can probably speak on both of these.
Uh, so on earlier packages I made, um, I knew people would land on different
pages, like of the, you know, reference API.
So my solution there was to, for each of those pages, no matter how small the
little thing was, I would have examples there too, because they show you the end
product and you can work your way backwards.
If you like the end products and this page is the page for you and you land on
the right page and you have some working code there as well.
Uh, so I resolved to do that.
It was very time consuming to write all these examples.
Um, but it was worth it because you never know where people land and they may just
bounce and give up if they don't find anything right away.
So you have to anticipate people will land in the weirdest spots.
Uh, we should, you should show something useful, I think, in every spot they land.
And in terms of an LLM, um, you know, helping it through, um, I mean, these
days it does a pretty good job, like finding where it has to go.
Um, I would have said like, you know, months ago, uh, you know, give it more of
a hand, but I think these days, at least when I used it or when I use agents, it
does find things pretty fast and it, it does bounce around a little bit, but it
does eventually land on land on the right things.
And depending on the documentation may have to go into like the source code, but,
um, usually the documentation does enough and it's truthful and current.
Uh, it's even better.
It doesn't have to stumble over the documentation.
Um, so I don't know about the second one.
Maybe, maybe we don't have to think about that soon.
Maybe LLMs, just agents just get better and it's not an issue.
Go ahead, James.
Uh, on, on Tom's point that there is some necessary organizational
structure to these documentation.
I actually agree quite a bit.
Cause if you think about the non-linearity, it's not a random
order in which I consume the units of documentation.
What it is, is it's an order that is subordinated under desiring to build
like a world model for how this works.
So for Matplotlib, I'll try and figure out what are the boundaries of the core
concepts, and I'll look for pieces that then allow me to reconstruct that.
Cause usually for tools like pandas and Matplotlib, the ideas of the
library are very rarely explicated.
Like the pandas documentation doesn't really highlight index alignment.
The Matplotlib documentation probably talks about artists and things like
that, but not in a way that surfaces it in any, you know, the assumption
is nobody actually cares, but in fact, this is what I care about.
As a consequence, when we look at the structure of the docs, the docs
are usually structured in a very kind of reference based authoritative.
Either, you know, this is, this is easy.
This is medium.
This is hard.
These are aligned in this fashion, but in truth, the non-linearity arises
because what I want to do is find disparate examples that then allow me
to formulate hypotheses about the underlying model, test those hypotheses
and then build that such that I no longer am reliant on the documentation.
So that if you have methods A, B and C, I learned method A, I learned method C
and I never read the documentation for method B because I can guess how method
B works from the model I've created.
From that perspective, I suspect that there might be an
organizational structure to these.
I don't know that anybody would actually use this or want this.
That is very, very different than the traditional organizational structures.
And I suspect that it may not be as idiosyncratic as it sounds, but it's
still going to be much, much different than what we look like.
Still very personalized.
And I think that there, I don't know whether you can get an LLM to
generate this in any usable fashion, but I think that this would, this
is effectively what I'm, what I'm doing, but painstakingly over a million
Google searches or a million LLM queries.
I wonder if like a, like a consistent use of C also, we provide, you know,
some, a number of like links to like other pages is like the way forward
because like, essentially then you have, you know, networking between
different parts of the API to each other.
And you don't have to limit it to like three things.
You can have as many as you want.
It's usually the below the example.
So it's even further down the page, but you know, less useful for a person,
maybe useful for a person, but definitely very useful for an agent that looks
for like linkages between things.
And if you're just like really rigorous in doing so, and even have an
LLM, like create that for you.
Like, I mean, I find that LLMs are really good at making documentation these days.
And it would be pretty good at just scanning your API and constructing that
essentially doing the optimal C also, you know, like chunks that you need in each
page.
I don't know that that might do it.
Excellent.
What do you think, Dan?
I guess I'll jump in with a quick, I guess we're just talking.
So it's a little bit of a subject shift, but you put a thought in my mind.
If the, if agents are really good at writing documentation, where do you need
to rein them in?
Cause I'm, I'm, I've seen it done.
We have some LLM written documentation, but I'm more nervous about that than
code somehow.
And it reminds me of an Onion article headline.
I saw AI summary of email longer than original email.
Yeah.
That's, that's, that's a bad case.
Um, but if I can get, you can have a skill just for like documentation writing,
have your own style, example pages, um, level of rigor, like how you want to
support examples, you know, like text before text after, um, how you section
things, like how, how much you nest sections with each other.
So your advice is like basically make a style guide or point it at your own
writing.
Yeah.
And, and have examples too, that it can hang by.
I think they have that.
And like the voice, things like that.
Um, yeah, you could do pretty well with just that one skill.
I, I shared Dan's concern about the robot, turning the robot loose on
documentation that, um, with code, at least you, they can run the tests and
compile and there's, it's very structured.
It will, it will happily produce plausible sounding English that uses some of the
same words as your project does that are utterly uncorrelated with what it
actually does.
I mean, I, I've, I've been trying to, to, um, uh, sorry, I'm freezing.
Cause I'm not sure it's an internal project.
I'm not sure if I can talk about it, but I was trying to use it to automate
writing doc strings for something, you know, many things we had that
organically, we were still here to the doc strings and it made some terrible,
terrible, terrible errors.
Like there's something called lockdown and it picked a plausible version of
lockdown.
That was not what that was doing.
So, yeah, I've had bad experiences in the past and I've also had bad experiences
with, with just tests, but that was a long time ago.
And now the test things, uh, the test case has been solved, I would say.
And, um, well, to grace, I mean, mostly, I mean, they, they work essentially.
They don't like fail immediately, but I say like docs, uh, in terms of agent LLM
written docs, they're, they're pretty good.
Again, you have to read them.
And, um, but if you have a good skill essentially, and you keep refining that
skill and keep, you know, I say, keep refining the skill and keep seeing what
it turns out, uh, it might be good for like, um, you know, a project that you
wish had docs and you don't want to act to have so much activation energy to get
to do it yourself.
Uh, I would, I would give her, give it a whirl.
It's not that bad.
Awesome.
With things in place that I'm going to preface with that.
Yeah.
And then James, some final thoughts to help close this out here.
As a feedback for Dan, might not our friend dietaxis be helpful here.
It seems like the LLM for purely reference style documentation is
somewhat innocuous in its use.
You can check very quickly and see if it's that, but anything that starts
to involve human judgment, for example, I was telling some of your DSSI
colleagues in my adventurous learning zig.
Um, I asked the LLM a bunch of questions and it tells me this is more elegant
or this is a better way to do things.
I skipped past that.
Anything that comes out of the LLM that is judgment based, even if the
judgment is 100% correct, I don't want to read it.
I don't want to hear it.
You are not a human being with stake in the game.
I simply do not care what you have to say.
I, the accuracy doesn't matter.
Even if it's a hundred percent correct, it doesn't matter.
I do not want to hear what a robot has to say.
And as a consequence, I think that from the documentation perspective, the
very opinionated documentation, that's where I would say, keep the LLM away from
it.
I really do not want to read that very, very violently.
Do not want to read that.
Right.
It's the, I don't want to ask people to read something that I
couldn't be bothered to write.
I think I'm still there, but I agree.
I was saying just for things like, like doc strings, like, uh, no, that's more
than fair.
Sure.
That's, that's fine.
But other things which are, you know, like the architecture and like how to use
you know, like best practices.
Definitely.
I would do that.
Yeah.
By oneself.
Fantastic.
Well, that takes us to the end of the time that we have here for today for
this month's Python exchange.
I want to thank all of our host panelists for joining and providing their thoughtful
and thought-provoking discussion points.
And of course, rich for joining and telling us all about great docs.
And finally, a huge thank you to everyone who has joined us today in our audience.
Whether you ask questions or are you listening in just to learn about this
project next month, we're going to be joined by Dan Yaw from Anaconda who works
on the Conda CLI and the broader packaging ecosystem.
So if you're interested in learning a little bit more about packaging, then
make sure that you check out our Python exchange next month, keep an eye out on
our website for more updates and the specific date and time that's meetup.doepy.org.
Thank you all for coming.
And I hope to see you all next time.
Have a great rest of your day.